<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: hardware | /dev/null]]></title>
  <link href="http://dev.slashnull.io/blog/categories/hardware/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dev.slashnull.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-31T03:23:01+12:00</updated>
  <id>http://dev.slashnull.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Modding the Happy Hacking Keyboard]]></title>
    <link href="http://dev.slashnull.io/blog/2013/09/05/modding-the-hhkb/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-05T22:45:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://dev.slashnull.io/blog/2013/09/05/modding-the-hhkb</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After reading <a href="http://grumpylemming.com/blog/2012/12/24/hacking-a-happy-hacking-keyboard/">this post about hacking your HHKB</a>, I set out to do the
same thing. It&rsquo;s just freaking awesome to have a keyboard with <strong>all your
favorite keybindings setup in the hardware</strong>. Basically I can now &lsquo;plug and
go&rsquo; into any computer and it automagically works.</p>

<p>Being able to do this goes beyond the sexy touch and feel of the HHKB. A
modded board is a entirely new beast, it&rsquo;s keyboard nirvana. No more feeling
awkward working on other computers! Just bring your extremely portable modded
keyboard ;)</p>

<p>Originally I was gonna go with a Teensy 2 and try to hack all the hardware
together, but <a href="http://geekhack.org/index.php?topic=12047.0">after finding this post on Geekhack</a> I decided
against risking my precious as a guinea pig for my first ever hardware mod,
instead I purchased a complete board from a guy who goes by <strong>hasu on
GeekHack</strong>. If you would like a more detailed guide about how to build this
mod yourself, <a href="http://grumpylemming.com/blog/2012/12/24/hacking-a-happy-hacking-keyboard/">Grumpy Lemming&rsquo;s guide</a> is a really good start.</p>

<p>Installation was surprisingly easy using Hasu&rsquo;s board. Everything was in the right
place - the board has a hole for the screw in the same spot as the original
board. He even made use of the dip switch location to expose the bootloader
reset button!</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/hhkb-1.jpg" width="600" title="Hasu&rsquo;s Controller Board" ></p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/hhkb-2.jpg" width="600" title="Taking it Apart" ></p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/hhkb-3.jpg" width="600" title="Bootloader Reset Button" ></p>

<p>I want to avoid turning this post into a guide, if you get the completed board
from Hasu it is extremely straightforward. For complete instructions on how to
set this up with a Teensy again check out the post above. I want to focus on
describing how I feel this new board has benefited me as a programmer, and why
anyone who uses a keyboard with heavily modified bindings should consider
this.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m sure that possibilities are limited only to your imagination, but here are
a few of my favorite tweaks that can be easily programmed with the
<a href="https://github.com/tmk/tmk_keyboard">tmk_keyboard repo</a>.</p>

<h2>#1 - Dual-purpose modifier keys</h2>

<p>For example, the following makes the left control key act as <code>&lt;ESC&gt;</code> when
tapped, and <code>&lt;CTRL&gt;</code> when held down.</p>

<pre><code class="cpp">static const uint16_t PROGMEM fn_actions[] = {
  // LControl with tap Esc*
  [2] = ACTION_MODS_TAP_KEY(MOD_LCTL, KC_ESC)
};
</code></pre>

<p>When working in VIM, you no longer have to reach up to the edge of the keyboard
in order to hit escape, just tap control on your home row :) This may take
some getting used to but I promise your fingers will thank you for it!</p>

<p>I realize the same thing can be achieved using something like
<a href="https://pqrs.org/macosx/keyremap4macbook/">KeyRemap4Macbook</a>. But overall the flexibility, portability and
feel-rightness makes this the superior option!</p>

<h2>#2 - Numpad on the home row</h2>

<p>The HHKB doesn&rsquo;t have a numpad. But the traditional numpad is out of reach and
disorientatin anyway. With my current setup I have a numpad centered around
<code>J</code> on my home row. When I hold tab (using the same dual-purpose modifier
strategy as before), the <em>numpad layer</em> is switched on, it looks like this:</p>

<pre><code>/* Layer 4: Numpad mode
  * ,-----------------------------------------------------------.
  * |Esc|   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |
  * |-----------------------------------------------------------|
  * |FN0  |  |   |   |   |   | 7 | 8 | 9 | = |   |   |   |Backs|
  * |-----------------------------------------------------------|
  * |Contro|   |   |   |   |   | 4 | 5 | 6 | + |   |   |Return  |
  * |-----------------------------------------------------------|
  * |Shift   |   |   |   |   |   | 1 | 2 | 3 | - |   |Shift |   |
  * `-----------------------------------------------------------'
  *       |Alt|Gui  |           0           |Gui  |Alt|
  *       `-------------------------------------------'
  */
</code></pre>

<p>With this setup, numeric input can finally feel like it&rsquo;s part of the flow!</p>

<h2>#3 - Vi Mode</h2>

<p>Although the HHKB comes with arrow key bindings, it never feels right after
prolonged use of VIM. My letter <code>f</code> key is now also dual purpose, and when
held down it activates vi-mode:</p>

<pre><code>/* Layer 2: Vi mode
  * ,-----------------------------------------------------------.
  * |Esc| F1| F2| F3| F4| F5| F6| F7| F8| F9|F10|F11|F12|Ins|Del|
  * |-----------------------------------------------------------|
  * |Tab  |  |   |   |   |   |   |   |PgU|   |   |   |   |Backs|
  * |-----------------------------------------------------------|
  * |Contro|   |   |PgD|FN0|   |Lef|Dow|Up |Rig|   |   |Return  |
  * |-----------------------------------------------------------|
  * |Shift   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |   |Shift |   |
  * `-----------------------------------------------------------'
  *       |Alt|Gui  |         Space         |Gui  |Alt|
  *       `-------------------------------------------'
  */
</code></pre>

<h2>#4 - Mouse Bindings</h2>

<p>Yep, you can control the cursor with your keyboard! This is just a
cool-showy-off thing but there have been some cases where this may be useful.
Again, this time I made the escape button on the top left dual purpose - press
for <code>&lt;esc&gt;</code>, hold for mouse mouse. In mouse mode <code>hjkl</code> control movement, and
the space bar is left click. Like so:</p>

<pre><code>/* Layer 3: Mouse mode
  * ,-----------------------------------------------------------.
  * |FN0| F1| F2| F3| F4| F5| F6| F7| F8| F9|F10|F11|F12|Ins|Del|
  * |-----------------------------------------------------------|
  * |Tab  |   |   |   |   |   |MwL|MwD|MwU|MwR|   |   |   |Backs|
  * |-----------------------------------------------------------|
  * |Contro|   |   |   |   |   |McL|McD|McU|McR|   |   |Return  |
  * |-----------------------------------------------------------|
  * |Shift   |   |   |   |   |Mb3|Mb2|Mb1|Mb4|Mb5|   |Shift |   |
  * `-----------------------------------------------------------'
  *      |Alt |Gui  |          Mb1          |Gui  |Alt|
  *      `--------------------------------------------'
  * Mc: Mouse Cursor / Mb: Mouse Button / Mw: Mouse Wheel 
  */
</code></pre>

<p>There must be plenty of other tweaks and hacks that I haven&rsquo;t thought of.
I&rsquo;m still continuously tweaking the key mappings in search of that holy grail of
key-bindings - it&rsquo;s been such an enjoyable experience.</p>

<h3>Updates</h3>

<p>Here are some other tweaks that I&rsquo;ve adopted so far:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><code>LSFT</code> becomes left parenthesis on tap, <code>RSFT</code> is right
parenthesis. This one actually came with the <code>tmk_keyboard</code> repo as an
existing macro, since there is no real key code to send for the parenthesis&#8217;.</p></li>
<li><p>Remap <code>esc</code> to <code>tilde</code>, I still can&rsquo;t get used to the replaced tilde
for escape next to the <code>1</code> key, since I&rsquo;ve got tap <code>LCTL</code> for escape now, no
longer need the original one.</p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
